Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY, 70 documents, 5 in Ms. and 65 printed, together
  - Lettera scritta da...Giuseppe Guerriri al Sig. Presidente Don Niccolò Caravita. Ms. in Italian. 10 pages. An account of the earthquake which struck Aquila in the Abruzzi, on Jan. 14, 1703. Niccolo Caravita (1647-1717), a Neapolitan law professor, is famous for having written a work, Nullum ius Romani Pontificis in Regnum Neapolitanum, in which he proves the invalidity of Papal claims to the Kingdom of Naples. The copy of this letter is dated: Aquila, March 9,...(1703). (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Veridica, e Distinta Relazione de i daneggiamenti causati dalle aescrescenze del Po in Mantova, Ferrara, e Pavia... Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1705. (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Breve, e Distinta Nototia Dell'antichissimo...Crocefisso...Di S. Lorenzo... Printed in Italian. 6 pages. N.pl., p.d. (Box 46, Folder 20)
  - Breve Relazione dell'Imagine della Gran Madre de Dio...in S. Marcello di Roma l'anno 1706 nell'Altare del B. Pellegrino. Printed broadside. 1 page in Italian. Folio, folded. With an engraved picture of the Madonna and Child. Rome, 1706. (Box 46, Folder 21)
  - Estatissima Descrizzione Di tutte le Feste...di S. Carlo 4 del presente Novembre 1709....In occasione del Giorno Natalizio...di Carlo Terzo... Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1709. (Box 46, Folder 22)
  - Vera Imago Acheropaeta SS. Salvatoris...à S. Domino Nostro Clemente Papa XI. Printed in Latin. 1 page. Small folio. With a woodcut representation of Christ. Rome, 1709. (Box 46, Folder 23)
  - Distinto Ragvaglio...nella Capella detta Sancta Sanctorum... Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 24)
  - Vera, e Distinta Relazione Della solenne Processione ...dalla Chiesa Santa Maria sopra Minerva alla Basilica Vaticana... Printed in Italian. 4 pages, 8vo. Rome, 1709. (Box 46, Folder 25)
  - Relazione del Celebre Miracolo di S. Giacinto... Fatto representar...il Cardinale Pietro Ottoboni... Printed in Italian. 4 pages, 8vo. Rome, n.d. (1711). (Box 46, Folder 26)
  - Altezza Reale... Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, large 4to. Publicata in Casale...2 Lugio 1713. A petition presented to King Vittorio Amadeo of Savoy by his Attorney General, Rivalta, a propos of some disturbances which occurred in the Cathedral of Casale Monferrato on the occasion of a solemn procession. (Box 46, Folder 27)
  - As a result of these disturbances, the Bishop of Casale had excommunicated Count Giacomo Nemours. To the petition is attached a copy of a decree issued by King Vittorio Amadeo on July 8, 1713, by which he declares the action of the bishop to be unjustified, and he takes action to correct it.
  - Relazione dell'Ingresso Solenne Nella Città di Narni Printed in Italian. 11 pages. Rome, 1709. (Box 46, Folder 28)
  - D.O.M. Ornamenti (Trionfi vol Armente detti) per le Tavole ...di...Papa Clemente Undecimo... Printed in Italian. 8 pages, 4to. Rome, 1713. (Box 46, Folder 29)
  - Descrizione del Publico Ingresso...in Roma li 12.Agosto 1714...dall'...Nicolo Duodo Ambasciator di Venezia...di...Clemente XI. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1714. (Box 46, Folder 30)
  - Ingresso in Rome dall'...Sig. Gio. Vinceslao di Gallas ...Il di 13.Maggio, 1714. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, (1714). (Box 46, Folder 31)
  - Descrittione del Corteggio...Data della Santità di...Papa Clemente XI...al Gio. Vinceslao di Gallas. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Rome, 1714. (Box 46, Folder 32)
  - Solenne Ingresso...in Roma...26.Luglio 1714 dall'Sig...Wolfgango Annibale Schrattembach. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Rome, 1714. (Box 46, Folder 33)
  - D.O.M. Ornamenti (Trionfi volgarmente detti)...di Papa Clemente XI. Anno MDCCXIV. Printed in Italian. 20 pages. Rome, 1714. (Box 46, Folder 34)
  - Dichiarazione Dell'Allegoria degl'Ornati... nel Palazzo Apostolico... Printed in Italian. 19 pages. Rome, 1715. (Box 46, Folder 35)
  - Veridica Relazione Della Infermità, e Morte..Re de Francia Luigi XIV... Printed. 4 Pages. Paris, Sept. 2, 1715. (Rome, 1715). (Box 46, Folder 36)
  - Illuminazione...in Roma per le Nascita dell'...Carlo VI. Printed in Italian. 12 pages. Rome, 1716. (Box 46, Folder 37)
  - Racconto delle Feste...in Roma ...si diede Sig. Papa Clemente XI della Nascita del...Leopoldo... Printed in Italian. 12 pages. Rome, 1716. (Box 46, Folder 38)
  - Relazione Succinta Delle Festività...in Vienna ...della...Nascita del...Leopoldo. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. (Rome?), 1716. (Box 46, Folder 39)
  - Dimostrazioni di Gioja per la Vittoria, & Acquisto di Belgrado. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Rome, 1717. (Box 46, Folder 40)
  - Relazione. Il Rè Giacomo III d'Inghilterra... Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, large 4to. 1717. (Box 46, Folder 41)
  - La Piu'Estatta, e Distinta Relazione Della Solenne Cavalcata...del Possesso presso Domenica 16.Novembre 1721...di Papa Innocenzo XIII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1721. (Box 46, Folder 42)
  - Motti, & Emblemi alludenti al Nome... Printed in Italian. 5 pages. Folio, folded. Rome, 1721. With a large engraving showing the procession. (Box 46, Folder 42a)
  - Veridico Ragvaglio...di Innocenzo XIII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages, folded folio, including an engraved portrait of the Pope, by Felippo Nevi, scul. Rome, (n.d.). (Box 46, Folder 43)
  - Descrizione della Macchina de'Fuochi di Gioja Fatti in Piazza di Spagna... l'Anniversario della Nascita...del Re Filippo V. Printed in Italian. 7 pages and large folded engraved plate "Dissegno della Macchina di Fuoco..." showing an arch of triumph...by Domenico Paradisi of Rome, architect to the Pope. (Box 46, Folder 44)
  - Relazione della Cerimonia...di Ludovico XV...di Francia. Printed in Italian. 11 pages. Rome, 1722. (Box 46, Folder 45)
  - Distinta Relazione...di tutte le Cerimonie della...Coronazione di...Benedetto XIII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1724. (Box 46, Folder 46)
  - Distinta Relazione della...Cavalcata in Occasione del Possesso preso dalla Santita di...Papa Benedetto XIII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. (Rome, 1724). (Box 46, Folder 47)
  - Veridica Relazione...di Papa Benedetto XIII Con... Descrizzione dell'Arco Trionfale. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Folded folio. (Rome, 1724). (Box 46, Folder 47a)
  - Hortus Conclusus. Machina de Fuochi Artificiali...in Loreto. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Ancona, 1726. (Box 46, Folder 48)
  - Relazione dell'Audienza Pubblica...Antonio Rambaldo. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Rome, 1730. (Box 46, Folder 49)
  - Relazione del Tremuoto Intesosi in Questa Città di Napoli. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Naples, 1732. (Box 46, Folder 50)
  - Relazione Succinta...accaduto in Ancona. Printed in Italian. 3 pages. Ancona, (1733). (Box 46, Folder 51)
  - Distinto Ragguaglio Del spaventoso Temporale, e Borasca di Mare...in Ancona. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Ancona, 1733. (Box 46, Folder 52)
  - Nella Solenne Fondazione della Prima Pietra del nuovo Lazzaretto in Isola ...in Ancona dalla... Beneficenza...Clemente XII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Folio. Ancona, 1733. (Box 46, Folder 53)
  - Relazione Essendosi deganta le Sanità di Nostro Signore. Printed in Italian. 4 pages, folio. Jesi, 1734. (Box 46, Folder 54)
  - Notitia del Giovanetto Inglese...alla fede Cattolica. Ms. in Italian. 6 pages. Ancona, May 1735. (Box 46, Folder 55)
  - Distinta Relazione delle Solenne Feste, e Illuminazioni Fatte in Napoli ...del felice Ritorno...di Carlo, Re di Napoli... Printed in Italian. 8 pages, 8vo. Naples, 1735. (Box 46, Folder 56)
  - Relazione del...Apparato e delle Sagre Funzioni...in occasione del Triduo ...in Roma...ad Onore della B. Michelina da Pesaro. Printed in Italian. 24 pages, 4to. Rome, 1737. (Box 46, Folder 57)
  - Relazione delle Funzioni...di Ravenna per l'Erezione della Statua di...Clemente XII. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Ravenna, (1738). (Box 46, Folder 58)
  - Distinta Relazione...da Raguaglio delle Ceremonie...doppo la morte...di Clemente XII. Printed in Italian and Latin. 4 pages. Rome, 1740. (Box 46, Folder 59)
  - Succinta Descrizzione...per il Funerale...di Clemente XII. Printed in Italian. 8 pages, 4to. Rome, 1740. (Box 46, Folder 60)
  - Relazione della...Elezione del...Benedetto XIV. Printed in Italian. 4 pages, small 4to.. Rome, 1740. (Box 46, Folder 61)
  - Compita, e distinta Relazione di Tutte le Funzioni...nella...Coronazione del...Benedetto XIV. Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome, 1740. (Box 46, Folder 62)
  - Distinta Relazione della Solenne Cavalcata...Benedetto XIV... With folded folio engraved plate of the "Cavalcata." Printed in Italian. 8 pages, 4to. Rome, 1741. (Box 46, Folder 63)
  - Distinta Relazione dell'Orrible Terremoto...di Aprile...1741, nelle Città di Camerino, Urbino, Pesaro, Jesi, e Fabriano... Printed in Italian. 4 pages. Rome and Velleteri, (1741). (Box 46, Folder 64)
  - Breve Relazione d'una Grazia Singloare...da S. Francesco Saviero...nella Chiesa del Gesu' di Roma. Printed in Italian. 8 pages. Rome?, 1744. (Box 46, Folder 65)
- DOCUMENTS FROM THE ROMAN CHANCERY, 6 documents, all in manuscript. Latin and Italian.
  188 pages. Folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, middle of the 18th century.
  - Acta Cancellariae Apostolicae ab Anno 1664 ad (1741). Ms. in Latin. 105 pages. Copies of acts from the Papal Chancellery. (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Congregazione 1741. Ms. in Latin. 1 page, 4to. (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Noma et Cognomina. Ms. in Latin. 1 page. List of the names of the Abbreviatores of the Presidenza Maggiores for 1664. (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Abbreviatores di Maggior Presidenza. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages. A petition to Pope Benedict XIII, dated Sept. 5, 1729, from his abbreviatores, asking for permission to use the surplice. (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Clement XII, Pope. Ms. in Latin, 3 pages. Copy of a Papal bull, dated February, 1735, acknowledging Clement's gratitude to Giuseppe Filippo Simonetti, one of his abbreviatores, appointing him to abbreviator literarum aposticolarum. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Clement XII, Pope. Ms. in Latin. 6 pages, 4to. A similar bull, conferring a similar appointment to Lazaro Opitio Pallavicini. Dated May 13, 1735. (Box 47, Folder 6)
- INTRODUTTIONE MATEMATICA...GEOGRAPHICHE
  - Introduttione Matematica Per La Intelligenza delle Tavola Geographiche. Manuscript in Italian. 165 pages. Small 4to. Limp vellum. Italy, probably 17th century. (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - A treatise on cartography, giving the mathematical basis for understanding and for drawing maps and plans.
- MISCELLANEOUS POEMS
  Three manuscripts, comprising 357 pages. 8vo. Limp vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - Lopez de Vega. Diversas Comedias: La Locura por la Hondra; El Perro del Hortulan; La Fortuna Merecida. Ms. in Spanish, 265 pages. (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Two Italian Poems: Ad Angelica. Love poem in octaves; Disaggi che si pateno ne le Carcere. Satirical poem in octaves on the discomforts of prison. Author unknown. Ms. in Italian. 12 pages, numbered ff. 137-143. (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Several poems in Italian. Manuscript. 80 pages. A collection of elegaic, satirical, and scatalogical poems. The sonnet on f. 147 is undoubtedly by Luigi Tansillo (1510-1568), and the other poems might also be by him. (Box 49, Folder 3)
- FIANO, O.L. CAPITOLI...DA OSSERVARSI...
  - Fiano, Orazio Ludovisio, Duke di. Capitoli e Leggi Da osservarsi inviolabilmente per ordine espresso dall' Santita di Nro. Sig. Dalle Milizie a piedi, et a Cavallo dello Stato Ecclesiastico. Manuscript. 136 pages. Folio. Contemporary limp vellum. Rome, 1622. (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript copy of a report by the General of the Papal troops, dated Rome, July 31, 1622, and printed in the Vatican in 1622.
- VARIOUS POEMS
  - Manuscript in Italian. 170 pages, 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, probably 17th century. (Box 50a, Folder 1)
  - An anthology of poems by the 16th century Italian poet Paolo Pacelli and others (?), all copied by the same hand, probably in the 17th century.
- ASTROLOGICAL AND ALCHEMICAL TEXTS, 2 treatises. Manuscript. 80 pages, 4to.
  Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, probably written in the 17th century.
  - Testis est mihi... Manuscript in Latin. 69 pages, numbered ff. 1-42v. With several diagrams. Treatise on Astrology, apparently a compilation. Author not given. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Camillo, Giulio. Fragmento delle tre transmutationi. Ms. in Latin. 14 pages, numbered ff. 43-50. Concerning Alchemy. Camillo was a Renaissance rhetotician and practitioner of mnemonics, etc. (Box 51, Folder 2)
- TREATISES ON THE ARTS OF LANGUAGE, 3 manuscript treatises. 256 pages. 8vo.
  Contemporary vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - (Cambiasi, Father ?). De Arte Retorica. Brevis Institutio. Ms. in Latin. 158 pages, numbered ff. 1-79v. A treatise on rhetoric, probably destined for students in Jesuit schools, by Father Cambiasi? On leaf 2 (r & v), a poem in honor of Cambiasi. N.pl., n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - De Arte Poetica. Brevis Institutio. Ms. in Latin. 57 pages, numbered ff. 81-109. A manual of Poetics. (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Brevis Tractatus de Epistolis. Ms. in Latin. 41 pages, numbered ff. 110-130. A treatise on letter writing. (Box 52, Folder 3)
- NEGOTIATIONI DI PACE...
  - Negotiationi di Pace delli signori Elettori di Magonza e di Colonia, fatte in Francoforto dalle Loro Altezze Elettoral, tra il...Duca di Grandmont et Signore di Lionne, Ambasciatori...di Francia, e il signor Conte di Peñaranda, Ambasciatore di Spagna, nell'anno 1658. Ms. in Italian. 172 pages, 4to. Contemporary vellum. Table of contents at the beginning. Italy, after 1658. (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - The French original was printed in Paris by Sebastian Cramoisy, Printer to the King and Queen of France, in 1658. This document relates to the Meeting of the Electoral Princes in Frankfurt in 1658 for the purpose of choosing an Emperor. The Emperor chosen was Leopold I, who was later involved in three wars, including the War of the Spanish Succession.
- DIARII DELLI VICERE' DI NAPOLI, E LORO GOUERNO.
  - Ms. in Italian. 995 pages. Thick 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. Table of contents at the beginning. Italy (Naples?), 17th century. (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Diarii delli Vicere di Napoli, e loro Governo. This volume contains the annals ( Diari ) of the Spanish Viceroys of Naples in the 17th century, with copious information about their governments. If not printed, historically very important material.
  - The Viceroys are: Pedro de Toledo; Cardinal Pacheco; Ferrante of Toledo, Duke of Alba; Cardinal de la Quena; Duke of Alcala; Cardinal Granvela; Marquis of Mandezar; Juan de Zuñiga; Pedro Giron, Duke of Ossuna; Juan de Zuñiga, Count of Miranda; Count Olivares; Hernando de Castro, Count of Lemos; Pedro Giron, Duke of Ossuna; Cardinal Zappata; Cardinal Gasparo Borgia; Cardinal Zappata; Duke of Alba.
- TREATISES ON ARISTOTLE, 6 treatises Ms. in Latin. 381 pages, 4to.
  Contemporary vellum. Italy, c.17th century.
  - In Aristotelis Meteorologica compendiaria commentatio. Ms. in Latin. 98 pages, including several blanks, numbered ff. 8-49. A resumé of the Meteorologia of Aristotle and other treatises. (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - De Horologiis solaribus Compendium. Ms. in Latin. 32 pages, numbered ff. 52-67v. With diagrams in text. (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - De Universi Mundi Sphaera. Ms. in Latin. 104 pages, numbered ff. 72-123. (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Digresso de Geographia Orbis. Ms. in Latin. 27 pages, numbered ff. 125-138. (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Aritmeticae practicae Compendium. Ms. in Latin. 78 pages, numbered ff. 139-177. (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - De Bellicis pauca. Ms. in Latin. 42 pages, numbered ff. 178-196v. This treatise contains some technical remarks on ballistics. (Box 55, Folder 6)
- MARETTI, LELIO. LA POLITICA...
  - Lelio Maretti, La Politica di...divisa in cento novantadue Capitoli, con le autoria e alleganzioni di Cornelio Tacito, Tito Livio, et altri classici authori antichi. Ms. in Italian. 1042 pages. Thick 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. Italy, probably first half of the 17th century. (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - This work on military science, by the Sienese nobleman Lelio Marretti, has presumably never been printed. The name of Marretti does not appear in the standard work on the history of military art, Jahn's Geschichte der Kriegswissenschaft; nor in the standard histories of Seicento Italian Literature, such as Pompeati, Belloni, or Renda-Operti: Dizionario della letteratura italiana.
- BOLVITO, GIOAN BATTISTA. LA ARME DE I RE DE NAPOLI.
  - Bolvito, Gioan Battista, La Arme de i Re de Napoli, raccolte..., insieme con una brevissima dicharazione della loro origine et dependencia. Ms. in Italian. 169 pages. Large 4to. Contemporary limp vellum. With drawings of coats of arms. Italy, c. 17th century. (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - The subject treated is the Coat of Arms of the King of Naples, with explanations as to their origins and connections.
- MISCELLANY, 3 manuscripts in Italian. 295 pages. 4to.
  - Spinola, Gherardo, Marchese d'Arquata. Memorie e Giornali d'un picciolo Viaggio fatto dal Sig...l'anno 1660. Ms. in Italian. 96 pages. An account of a trip taken by Gherardo Spinola through Germany, Austria, Hungary, etc. The complete list of cities is given on pp. 95-96. (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Cueva, Don Alfonso de la, Conte di Bedmar. Relazione di Venezia. Ms. in Italian. 240 pages, numbered ff. 97-266. This is the Report made by Alfonso de la Cueva (1572-1655), at the request of King Philip III of Spain, concerning Venice. He was Imperial Ambassador to that city. (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Bedmar is famous for having organized a plot to overthrow the government of Venice and had the reputation of being "one of the most powerful geniuses and one of the most dangerous minds Spain has ever produced." (Nuov. Biogr. Univ., Paris, 1855, vol. V, p. 127). This Relazione which he wrote after his ambassadorship (after the discovery of the plot, he was forced to flee Venice and take refuge in Flanders) may be the same as the ms. in Italian in the possession of the Library of Lyons. It is a document of prime importance.
  - Alcune notizie particolari delle cose di Venezia. Delle case nobili. Ms. in Italian. 29 pages. Some additional information on Venetian nobility. At the end is a list of houses belonging to the aristocracy. (Box 58, Folder 3)
- MISCELLANY, 66 documents, consisting of 58 manuscripts, 7
  printed broadsides, and 1 engraved plan. Comprising altogether 1082 pages. Folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, 17th and 18th century.
  - S. Biagio della Pagnotta. 12 ms. documents in Latin and in Italian. 135 pages, numbered ff. 1-85. Copies of documents concerning this church, its foundation, its architecture, members, inventory, etc. relating to inspections in 1725 and 1731. (Box 60, Folder 1-12)
  - Santa Caterina da Rota. 5 ms. in Latin and Italian, 45 pages, numbered ff. 86-111. Copies of documents concerning this church in Rome. 1735. (Box 60, Folder 13-17)
  - Narrazione dell'insigne Miracolo, operato da Dio per l'Intercessione del Glorioso S. Pietro...nella Sacrosancta Basilica Vaticana. Printed pamphlet, 10 pages, numbered ff. 112-117. Account of a miracle which occurred in the Anno Sancto 1725. Rome, G.M. Salvioni, n.d. (Box 60, Folder 18)
  - Relazione dell'Incoronazione della Beatissima Vergine della Neve...nella Citta di Cortona fatta dall'Gio. Andrea Ricci... Ms. in Italian, 20 pages, numbered ff. 118-127. Dated Oct. 8, 1741. (Box 60, Folder 19)
  - Ricci, Gio. Andrea. Orazione...in occasione della Coronazione fatta in Montepulciano della Miracolosa Madonna delle Grazie. Ms. in Italian. 5 pages, numbered ff. 130-132. Dated Sept. 24, 1741. (Box 60, Folder 20)
  - Apone, Don Filippo. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 134-135. Account of the abjuration of a Filippo Apone on March 26, 1706. (Box 60, Folder 21)
  - Funeral Rites for the Queen of England. Ms. in Italian. 9 pages, numbered ff. 136-140. The Queen (probably Maria Clementina, the wife of the Old Pretender) was buried in St. Peter near Christina of Sweeden. Jan. 18, 1735. Includes a full page drawing of a chalice. (Box 60, Folder 22)
  - Cuneo. Engraved plan of the city and its fortifications. oblong folio, folded. Undated and unsigned. (Box 60, Folder 23)
  - Juramentum prestandum a Canonicis in adeptione canonicatuum. Ms. in Latin. 1 folio page, folded. Undated. (Box 60, Folder 24)
  - Charles VI. Diploma awarded by Emperor Charles VI to Cardinal Borromeo on his taking possession of Parma and Piacenza. Printed broadside in Latin. Large folio, folded. Dated Milan, Jan. 21, 1731. (Box 60, Folder 25)
  - Pamfili, Cardinal Benedetto. Il Figliol' Prodigo. Ms. in Italian. 20 pages, numbered ff. 145-154. An oratorio. Undated. (Box 60, Folder 26)
  - Morei, Michel Giuseppe. Nella morte del Sommo Pontefice Clemente XI. Canzone. Ms. in Italian. 9 pages. Poem on the death of Pope Clement XI (1721). (Box 60, Folder 27)
  - Domenica 10 Ottobre. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 165-166. A mass celebrated on occasion of the victory in Hungary. (Box 60, Folder 28)
  - Three sonnets on various states of human life. Ms. in Italian. 6 pages, numbered ff. 167-170. (Box 60, Folder 29)
  - Two sonnets. Ms. in Italian. 2 pages, numbered ff. 171-172. 8vo. One sonnet on Eugene of Savoy, the other to the Imperial ambassador Count Gallas. (Box 60, Folder 30)
  - Two canzonettas. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages, numbered ff. 179-183. (Box 60, Folder 31)
  - Relazione dell'arrivo della flotta Spagnola a Palermo. Ms. in Italian. 8 pages, numbered ff. 185-188. The Spanish fleet's arrival at Palermo on July 1, 1718. (Box 60, Folder 32)
  - Another copy of the above (no. 32). Ms. in Italian. 12 pages, numbered ff. 189-194. (Box 60, Folder 33)
  - Louis XIV's Death. Ms. in Italian. 16 pages, numbered ff. 195-202. Account of the death of the French King on Sept. 1, 1715. (Box 60, Folder 34)
  - Derwentwater, Count James. Discorso. Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 203-204. Speech by the Count prior to his decapitation for high treason against King George I in London on Tower Hill, on Feb. 24, 1716. (Box 60, Folder 35)
  - Londra, 9 Marzo 1716, Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 205-206. Report from London concerning the Jacobite rebellion, attempts to save Derwentwater, and other political events. (Box 60, Folder 36)
  - Alexander VII, Pope. Ms. in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 207-208. Resume of a speech by the Pope to the committee appointed to deliberate on controversial ecclesiastical matters, held on Jan. 30, 1691. (Box 60, Folder 37)
  - Relazione del seguito nella venuta di Giovanni Andrea Poicet (?) in Montepulciano per coronare La Beata Vergine detta di S. Martino... Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 209-210. Undated. (Box 60, Folder 38)
  - Clement XI, Pope. Ms. in Latin. 4 pages, numbered f. 211. Nov. 11, 1703. (Box 60, Folder 39)
  - Chi sia lecito in questo... Ms. in Italian. 4 pages, numbered ff. 213-214. A sermon, undated. Apparently for Easter. (Box 60, Folder 40)
  - Mi sia lecito in questo giorno... Ms. in Italian. 25 pages, numbered ff. 215-226. An undated sermon. Apparently a draft, with numerous corrections. (Box 60, Folder 41)
  - Diario della legazione...da...Clemente XI... Ms. in Italian. 72 pages, numbered ff. 227-264. Journal of the legation sent by Pope Clement XI to Elizabeth Farnese, wife of King Philip V of Spain. With a complete list of persons forming the legation. (See Vol. 33, #22). (Box 60, Folder 42)
  - Gozzadini, Cardinal Ulisse Giuseppe. Printed speech in Latin. 19 pages, numbered ff. 265-273. Faenza, J.A. Archus, 1717. To the people of Ravenna. (Box 60, Folder 43)
  - Palatius, Jacobus. Ritus Sacrarum Ceremoniarum ad Usum Ecclesiae Principis Apostolorum de Urbe. Ms. in Latin. 46 pages, numbered ff. 274-296. On the rites to be observed in Roman churches. Undated. (Box 60, Folder 44)